- Welcome to Anxiety Algorithms and Gen Z,
Generative AI
and student mental health.
We're so excited.
Yay.
- [Attendee] Woo.
(audience applauding)
- We're so excited to see you all.
I'm gonna do panelist bios.
I always take a lot of time
for bios when I moderate a panel
because why do we wanna hear from these experts?
What's their expertise?
What do they bring to the table,
that's worth taking a little time to discover.
So I'm gonna start with Dr. Xuan Zhao,
a national expert in the psychology
of social connection, wellbeing,
and human AI interaction.
She's a behavioral scientist at Stanford University
and the CEO and co-founder of Flourish Science,
a public benefit startup
translating behavioral science
into everyday tools for emotional wellness.
Her work has been featured in major news outlets
and under her leadership Flourish AI
has supported students
across 200 plus campuses.
Won the 2024 Stanford Ed Tech Award
and led the Nation's first Wellbeing AI study
of which Foothill College is a key partner.
Let's all welcome Dr. Zhao.
(audience applauding)
Next we have Alex Kraft.
Alex Kraft graduated summa laude
from Chapman University
in 2025 with a BA in psychology.
And as a member of the University honors program.
She has conducted research at Stanford UCSF
and Chapman on topics ranging from virtual reality
interventions to belonging and mental health.
In addition to her research,
Alex has experience
in crisis counseling and psychotherapy
and currently works
as a research assistant at Flourish Science supporting
studies utilizing their app-based tools
for emotional wellbeing.
Welcome Alex.
(audience applauding)
And then finally on the end here we have Gil.
Gil Perez is a full-time tenured personal counselor
at College of San Mateo.
As a faculty leader,
he has helped transform the mental
health model at his institution
and in the CCC system to ensure students have flexible
and broad mental health services
that meet the full range
of mental health needs.
He works with student support programs
and instructional programs
to deliver mental health programming
that are culturally responsive
and advance the educational mission, vision
and values of the college.
He provides direct mental health services to students,
consultation to faculty
and staff, serves as a clinical supervisor
and oversees the mental health
peer educator program,
as well as the chapter advisor for Active Minds.
Excellent.
(audience applauding)
I will be y'all's panel moderator today.
My name is Trudi Radtke,
I'm an instructional technologist
designer for Mort Park College.
I'm also an AI fellow at the Chancellor's office.
I'm conducting a lot of research in AI literacy
and my background is in primarily ed tech.
And then I also have a background in policy
and open access research and advocacy.
So without further ado, we're gonna get started.
Our first question is for Gil,
opening and framing of this conversation.
From your perspective on the CCC Mental Health
and Wellness board,
what new mental health trends are you
seeing among community college students?
How are these needs similar to
or different from those at four year institutions?
- I just wanna say good afternoon.
Good afternoon everyone.
I want to thank you all for choosing to be with us
for the panel today.
So I do want to start off with some statistics
to start us off.
These statistics are from NAMI and Active Minds.
50% of mental health conditions begin by age 14
and 75% begin by age 24.
So I want us to think about lived experiences,
cumulative experiences,
traumatic life events,
other experiences of our students that contribute
to anxiety, depression, and suicide ideation.
We know there are global events,
violence, climate change,
immigration, separation and deportation.
And by the time our students reach college,
they're also navigating an entirely new environment.
There's pressure to succeed and meet familial
and societal expectations,
be financially stable
and future focused.
And this can really exacerbate
isolation and loneliness
because of competition, comparisons with their peers,
very strenuous study schedules, sleep deprivation,
and not feeling like they have time for friends, family,
or making new friends.
And so from my work with Gen Z over the years,
I am seeing more of an openness
to talk about mental health.
And there are different platforms for them
to use their voice or share their story.
That includes social media.
We see podcasts, they're going live,
there's more peer-to-peer programming
that are happening on campus.
And at the same time, we know
that stigma is still pervasive.
So our colleges are uniquely positioned
to meet the mental health needs of today's students
by offering relevant support
and ensuring that we're broadening the options
for mental health care
that is inclusive of digital care
to support prevention, early intervention
and treatment of mental health issues for our students.
And I also want
to highlight loneliness is a significant issue
that we are also positioned to address on our campus.
The US surgeon General declared loneliness,
a public health epidemic comparing its health risk
to smoking 15 cigarettes a day.
If folks haven't heard that before.
And what I'm seeing in my practice,
I'm seeing Gen Z turn
to AI for connection and care.
It's so easy to go to ChatGPT
to validate their feelings,
empathize with their situation.
AI is there for them.
And I've heard students even call AI,
ChatGPT, their best friend. (chuckles)
So it becomes a form of companionship,
but we know AI is not a replacement
for real human connection.
- Fantastic, thank you Gil.
Our next question is for Xuan,
anxiety is at the heart
of this panel's title, recent bestsellers,
like "The Anxious Generation", have argued
that Gen Z is growing up
in uniquely stressful conditions.
Why do you think this generation is often described
as quote, the most anxious in the US
and most importantly for our audience listeners,
how does AI amplify or relieve that anxiety?
- Yeah.
It's really hard to be a young person nowadays.
I don't envy them at all.
In fact, there's a recent study, very interesting,
so the Happiness Report,
world Happiness report comes out every year
and used to be happiness used to be a U-shaped curve.
That is when you're young
or when you're old, you're happy.
And people in the middle sandwich
in the middle are the least happiest.
But now it's a linear increase
that is the older you are, the happier you are.
Young people are the least happiest now.
And speaking of anxiety,
that's also a big issue.
So 10 years ago depression
was the biggest mental health
challenge, but nowadays,
anxiety there's been across over a few years ago.
So who here have read this book,
"The Anxious Generation" by Jon Hyde?
We have at least two people, three, four, yes.
Highly recommend, very interesting book about
analyzing the anxiety problem our young people have.
Of course there are some scholarly debate about some
of the arguments here, but I think overall
my takeaways are one,
the reason why we are seeing
such an increase in anxieties
is because increase of screen time,
smartphone, social media
and combined with decrease of in-person time,
face-to-face time, free play.
So combined people actually social media
and tech screen, they contribute lots of issues.
So social comparison, loneliness, isolation,
and also anxiety by, you know, comparing
with the standard out there,
what you perceive to be the standard.
So that's why I think really
it's uniquely challenging now.
And I think now AI is coming.
AI is a really interesting tool.
It can actually have the opportunity
to amplify the challenges,
the problems we are seeing right now,
'cause AI can be even more addictive,
more personalized,
more echo chamber a very,
we know the AI can be very
affirming, right?
It can actually not challenging what you say
and that is one path.
But the other path is AI,
we can actually use it
to help students build coping strategies
that they don't get
to practice in using social media
or using their screen to nudge them to reach out
to other people, to help them
to set up reminder just in time when
their mind is going in spiraling.
So the choice is how are we going to design
these kind of technology and how schools
and other stakeholders are going to promote (indistinct),
you know, well intended scientifically grounded ways
to use AI rather than letting students wander onto,
you know, some harmful tools.
And that might seem fun,
but could be dangerous in the long run.
So I would say scientific grounding, ethical design,
and also clinical guidance.
Those are all really important things when we think about
building AI that can be useful for mental health
and even revert the trend
we are seeing with social media.
- Fantastic.
I really like that point, especially
that students are gonna use it.
So we might as well have an option for them
that is research based, that is scientific,
give them choices that are good choices versus just having
them run to the first thing,
which is generally ChatGPT.
- Yeah.
Can I just share two points?
Students already using it.
So in '24, 2024, the most common use case
for gen AI was idea generation.
But in 2025 it's therapy and companion.
So people are already using this.
It's the most common way people use it nowadays.
And for recently Common Sense Media,
they did a research
study on, in this case teens,
not college students,
but they found that 76% of teens have used AI companion.
Half of them say that they use it regularly.
So yes, they are already using it now.
I think teaching AI literacy,
what are good ways to use AI
for emotional, mental, wellbeing support,
what are some dangerous ways to use it?
That's really important.
- Absolutely, absolutely.
I think literacy is at the heart
of a lot of these conversations.
This question is for Alex.
As a student leader
and a student leader in peer support,
how do you see your peers relationships
with AI and mental health?
Is AI adding to their stress
or are students beginning
to use it as a tool for support?
- Yeah, so as you might expect, it's both
on the stressor side,
we're obviously seeing concerns over the job market,
which was already not too great for us.
I just graduated.
I am, you know,
working as a nanny.
So that says that.
But I think that for a lot of fields outside of, you know,
myself, I have friends in,
you know, computer science
or business and there's a lot of concern that a lot
of these entry level
job positions are gonna be replaced
by AI and we are already seeing it
and we're seeing that a lot
of these companies now want
their employees to be able
to use AI and have AI literacy to make sure that they,
you know, can be the most efficient workers
and that it wouldn't make more sense
to just replace them completely with AI.
So that's definitely a big area
that I'm seeing my peers struggling with.
And then also in terms of school, there's a lot
of talk obviously about using AI for classwork
and so it, there's an ethical struggle there
because you know, sometimes it's, yeah,
it's great for bouncing ideas off of
and it's great for you know, organizing stuff,
but then there's a question
of when does it become the AI doing your work for you
and how is that impacting
your critical thinking skills?
And you know, we're seeing that, you know,
some job fields are feeling
that the entry level individuals
they are getting aren't
as prepared as in the past.
And a reason for this is possibly because of AI use
and not having the same level
of critical thinking skills.
So there's that.
And then in terms of AI literacy,
people would think that Gen Z, you know,
has the best skills.
They know how to use AI, they know how to avoid
wrong answers, but in reality we're seeing
that even though Gen Z is quite dependent on it,
they're not able to catch
when it's doing something wrong
or giving a bad answer.
So that's definitely detrimental as well.
But on the positive side of things,
as kind of discussed AI
for mental health support has been really great.
I have a lot of friends who have, yeah,
as kind of discussed use ChatGPT
as their personal therapist as a friend.
And we're seeing that this is a great kind of way
for like entry level mental health help for people
who either can't afford therapy
or are a little hesitant to it.
So it's a low, you know, entry point
for mental health assistance,
which I think can definitely spur
a lot of change in terms
of pushing individuals
to seek out formal therapy eventually as well.
And you know, there's no stigma,
they're not worried about judgment, et cetera.
And yeah, I think that's kind of the two main things.
Yeah.
- That was really excellent,
Alex, I also really like that barrier
to entry point you made as being a hurdle to therapy
and how there is potential,
there is already potential
that AI is like a way to jump that hurdle.
Excellent.
This is for Gil, career anxiety is one
of Gen Z's biggest stressors, especially
with AI reshaping the future of work.
How is this showing up among students
and what can colleges do to help them navigate
that uncertainty?
- Yeah, so I'm definitely seeing career anxiety
as a stressor of our students, especially
with AI reshaping the future of our work.
I think there's a lot of uncertainty about
how AI will affect career choices
and decisions that our students make.
And I think what I'm seeing is that it is
influencing them in a way where they're trying
to see if there's a way to avoid it.
So they're choosing more hands-on careers,
healthcare, trade programs.
And what I'm also learning
through our future summit today
is that our, you know,
a lot of our entire workforce is being reshaped by AI.
So it's not something that they can necessarily avoid.
So these are things that if we're,
it's great if it's their intrinsic reason,
but if their decision making
is based on a perceived threat
of AI, that's definitely
worth exploring with our students.
I think also students already
outside of AI may struggle
with their sense of worth just as an individual.
And so the systems
that our students exist
in can make students feel like
they're not enough
or that they're not doing enough.
And so it's not uncommon for people
to tie their self-worth to their work.
Okay.
And so if they're hearing
that AI is taking over positions, there's this idea
that AI has more value than people
and that can create self-doubt, self-criticism,
it can worsen anxieties, leaving people
to really question their own value,
what's left for them if AI can already
do parts of their their job.
And so career anxiety is not just about worries
for stability and a good paying job,
it's also about their identity and purpose.
And so I think our California community colleges,
especially what I'm seeing throughout our summit,
you know, we really are leading our AI revolution,
creating new career narratives.
And so hearing what's happening in the workforce
development, I do feel hopeful
hearing our students are the ones building the future.
I also am hearing professors
and how they're integrating AI literacy
into their curriculum.
And so there are ways we can learn to use AI ethically
and work alongside it.
I heard great examples
of how professors are working with AI
by having students really show how they use AI ethically
and responsibly and not avoid it.
And so there are things like internships, career fairs,
workshops, guest speakers.
I think there's more opportunities we can utilize
to bring industry experts to discuss
how AI is shifting roles
and what skills are most needed,
what job options there are in the field,
and how we can still continue
to combine human creativity, critical thinking
with the efficiency of AI.
I think like, again, you're gonna hear this
more than once for me, but like AI
or not, I think our students,
because they're still learning, there's a lot
that they don't know about career fields
'cause they're not in them yet.
There's a lot that they don't know about it, right?
There's a lot of what they hear.
And so I do think it's important for them to, you know,
hear from the experts so that they can,
which can also support
some of that career anxiety around
how AI is reshaping the fields,
'cause again, they're,
the anxieties could promote them
to want to run away, (laughs), versus really address
what skills they need to know
to really compliment human work with AI.
I also think our educators need to continue to,
you know, model a growth mindset
by continuing our own professional development
and AI so that we are keeping current
with emerging technologies similar to making time
to this last couple days for our summit.
I'll quickly just give an example.
Like when COVID first hit,
there was a lot of fears
of going virtual for like our mental health services
in the CC system.
People were like there's no way we can do telehealth.
Like it was really only seen
as a model of in-person care
and we learned ethical telehealth use
and that really transformed our mental health model
and now it's a service we don't go without, right?
Like it's increased access for our students.
And I think this is something
we can also adapt to regarding AI.
And so I think our Gen Z students,
they have the right
to feel excited and nervous,
but I think we want them
to be able to see that there's room
for both and all, right, so they can
make room for their identity, their purpose
and technology can coexist with it.
- Fantastic Gil, thank you.
I also really like the perspective,
I'm hearing this a lot from the panelists,
like this access barrier,
like this barrier to entry.
If AI can remove that in terms
of getting mental health help,
I think that's incredible.
Whether, you know, we may have our doubts about it,
et cetera, but removing barriers to entry is what we,
especially I feel like community colleges do best.
So that's very interesting.
This next question is for Xuan,
Flourish is a purpose built research validated AI app
for student mental health.
Why AI and what opportunity
do you see AI play in promoting
student mental health?
- Awesome.
I'll continue on access.
So, well, one question is access for who, right?
Because in the past when we think
about therapy counseling,
usually students who are already struggling
and they may have been quietly
sitting with the challenges
for months and finally decide to reach out for help.
And we know how long students sit
with the challenges without asking for help.
So what's really cool about AI
and this is how we think
about mental health,
is that mental health is a continuum.
Like maybe 15% of people are in the red zone.
They are deeply in a concerning state,
maybe clinically depressed
or anxious, they need professional support.
But then there are, let's say 80%
of people in the yellow zone
or orange zone, maybe having
their fair share of rejections
or stress moments when they feel demotivated
or stressed out, they may have conflict
with their peers or their parents
or their colleagues.
And then they may also have
at night have racing thoughts, can't fall into sleep.
So they are not in the clinical side of things.
They may not seek out for mental health support.
Also because it can be expensive,
the waiting time can be long.
But with AI it can actually guide people
to learn coping strategies
and to make better sense
of what they are going through
and take actions to improve it,
to move towards the green zone.
So that's how we started thinking about AI.
So we founded Flourish with
another colleague from Stanford,
Department of Psychology.
And the way we think about
AI is not as AI therapist,
I think that's the wrong way to think about AI.
When whenever people say AI therapist,
I'm like, no, no, no.
At least that's not what we are building.
It's actually how we think about AI
as a recommendation engine.
Think about it.
So there has been decades
of research in psychology, social psychology,
positive psychology, a wide range
of literature about science-based actions you can do
to improve your mental health, your wellbeing,
your social relationship to better connect
with other people, find more motivation,
overcome procrastination, as not reaching people.
And oftentimes you have
to go through some lots of books
or listen to podcasts to find something
that's relevant for you.
But with AI you can ask AI a question about
what you're going through right now
and give you the most relevant knowledge and action.
So that is the power that we think about AI.
It surfaced the most relevant knowledge
and action at the right time.
So with that, we actually found
it Flourished towards
the end of 2022 when ChatGPT came out.
And that's how we have been approaching AI.
So when we work with schools, usually we emphasize
that this is mental health promotion, prevention
and early intervention.
So the deep work should be left
to psychologists and therapists.
But teaching coping strategies, helping students
to stop spiraling
and actually taking positive action,
checking with them,
build positive habits
and celebrate them for showing
up to all those good habits
that I think AI can play a very unique role.
And one last thing I want to emphasize is at Flourish we
call a what we are building,
the AI is the STAR framework.
So STAR stands for science-based.
It needs to be grounded in empirical research.
STAR, T is timely.
So what's the most relevant knowledge
and action and A is action.
So no matter how much you talk with AI,
if you don't take action
or maybe you read books, listen to podcasts.
If you don't take action, nothing's gonna change.
You can read all the books about self care
and still live, you know, still struggle
with your wellbeing,
have to take small actions
even when you are spiraling,
maybe just stop taking three deep breaths
or when you are, you know,
when you are struggling
to get out of the bed,
maybe just think about opening the window
and just get some fresh air.
So there are so many small things that can do
that can really change the trajectory.
So small actions, big impact.
So that's A, and finally, R is real life focused.
How can we nudge people to better connected
with their friends, their communities,
not just with AI?
So that is how we think about AI,
the unique role
that AI plays in this innovation.
- Fabulous, fabulous.
This next question is for Alex.
You have conducted an independent research project
on the Flourish app.
Can you tell us what you found in the study
and what you heard from your peers?
- Yeah, so I had the opportunity to work
with some Flourish pilot data with
around 500 students surveyed, basically
where we looked at the impacts
of Flourish use versus a control.
And one of the main outcomes we found was
that there was a significant increase in positive motion
or measured by positive effect,
which is basically
domains including calm, wellbeing, vigor.
And with this analysis, I thought, I wonder
what some moderators could be.
Moderators are basically things
that impact the significance,
the strength of the relationship.
And so in the fact
that this was a college student sample,
one thing that a lot of college students face is stress.
So I said, hey, we have stress measured,
we're taking baseline stress,
we're taking measures
of it throughout the study,
let's compare it to the end result.
And in this moderator analysis,
we did actually find
that stress was a significant moderator.
And what this basically meant
is that the individuals
who used Flourish that had a greater baseline stress,
they had greater improvements
in their positive effect over
this six week study period.
And I think this type
of data is really interesting
when you think about
who these positive psychology tools
are the most useful for.
And in talking to my peers, I had a couple friends
who actually partook in the study
because it was done partially at my university.
So that was cool.
But it was interesting
because the ones who I think had higher stress
in their lives, who did feel they benefited
the most Flourish,
almost acted as a way to, you know,
line out their life in a way
that made it easier for them
to handle everything, to evaluate what needed
to be focused on, their schoolwork,
their social life, their relationships.
And then the individuals who, you know,
felt like they handled their stress pretty well.
The ones who felt like
they didn't really need a wellness app to help,
but you know, they were put in the experiment group,
they didn't feel it was as useful,
but it was still useful,
'cause we did see that there was generally a significant,
you know, increase in positive effect over time.
So just looking at
that I think is really important when it comes
to developing these apps as well
and catering them to the individuals
that do need them the most,
such as high stress college students.
So yeah.
- Fantastic.
Thank you Alex.
All right, we're gonna move on to a real world
implementation question,
but before we do,
I'm just gonna say a little aside.
So I would say I'm a bit of a curmudgeon
when it comes to AI and mental wellness.
I think that I've definitely,
I'm clinically depressed
so I fall on that 15%
and I've been using the Flourish app
for about the past two weeks in preparation.
for this panel, I did not know that.
And I will say that I was really encouraged
because as Xuan mentioned,
the first point in STAR being science-backed,
there are mental health applications out there
that run on AI that aren't science-based,
they're not built
by researchers, et cetera, et cetera.
And I think that it's important to note the importance
of having people who know what they're doing,
develop these types of things.
We see that a lot in AI literacy,
not using it isn't a really good option,
students are gonna use it.
So directing them to tools
that are gonna be research-based
and science-based as a researcher,
I really appreciate that.
And the other couple of points about prevention
and intervention, like catching them where they're at.
I mean I found it to be quite frankly, really useful.
I mean I was really not motivated
to work out the last week,
but Flourish was like,
what if we reframed this positively
and what if instead of putting
all this pressure on yourself
to do an hour workout,
you just like did it felt good
and moved your body a little bit?
And it helped, it did because it just,
it was like a quick
reframe when I needed it.
So I like the point that like we still have
those groups that they're gonna need
professional counseling, right?
Like this is not a replacement to that,
but I like that Flourish doesn't position
or posit itself as that, it's an intervention app.
And yeah, I really am as a curmudgeon,
I really enjoyed it.
So I just wanted to have that aside really quick.
Alright, so this is our real
world implementation question.
This is for Xuan.
You've partnered with colleges like Foothill.
In fact, we've received
a testimonial from Alexis Donato,
department chair of the health center.
She's in a mandatory training
and wasn't able to be here today.
She was supposed to be on the panel,
but she provided a two page letter of support for this.
And here's a paragraph that I found intriguing,
which I'm gonna read to you all now.
"In our ongoing search for evidence-based,
scalable and cost-effective tools
to enhance student mental wellbeing,
Flourish has stood out
as a best in-class solution.
While we have explored various digital mental health
platforms, Flourish is one of the few
that seamlessly integrates behavioral science,
emotion regulation strategies
and proactive digital engagement into a platform
that feels accessible and affirming
to community college students.
The app is not just a repository of tools," that is true,
I've used it, "It's a self-learning companion
that meets students where they're at
and supports them in building healthier habits,
managing stress and cultivating resilience.
With its AI powered companion,
Sunny Flourish brings warmth
and encouragement to a process of mental health support,
something that is especially critical for students
who may not feel comfortable
accessing traditional services
or who are underserved by the existing systems."
So with that note in mind, Xuan,
what have you learned from those collaborations
and about what makes digital
mental health intervention
succeed or fail on campuses?
- Thank you.
I'm blushing right now.
I think the, what really gives
me a sense of meaning is
to hear when people are benefiting
from what we have built.
It's not a easy path, definitely no.t
Building startup, building a product
and trying to figure out how to promote it.
It's all new things
I've been learning over the years
and I'm so grateful for our campus partners
for supporting us such as Foothill.
They are the very first campus partner,
now we've reached over 200 campuses
and we have official school-wide collaborations,
partnerships with almost 10 different
universities and colleges.
Foothill remains to have
a very special place in my heart
because they were the first one to jump on board.
I think what we have learned,
one is the product has to be really engaging.
The reason why Foothill decided to go with us is
because they had a mental health app before
and students were not engaging with it
and it felt very corporate like, so it feels,
it doesn't vibe with Gen Z.
So when they brought Flourish they gave this
to students and students tested out, oh by the way,
if you can also try it out,
it's just on the App Store
or Google Play, you can search Flourish,
you'll see how cute it is.
We're shamelessly cute.
So this Sunny, also this is Sunny,
this little sun character.
So we chose the sun as this metaphor, the companion
because we are both like sun
giving warmth to other people
and we also like plants
receiving the warmth from other
people as we grow.
So we really like this sun character
and we have really waved this whole metaphor
into this entire app and also
have so many engaging animations,
badges, you know, progress tracker, habit building,
you know, so all of those is to create this sense
that wellbeing is not something so heavy
and so sad when you know,
it's the turning this deficit
based model narrative about
mental health around to mental wellness, right?
So a strengths based approach, public health approach.
So that's how I think
that really helps Flourish stand out.
And this is similar,
we have heard similar stories from other campuses.
So for example, Villanova University,
they on the east coast, they have a really
strong sport team.
Do we have alumni there?
- [Attendee] My daughter.
- Your daughter, a Villanova parent.
Yes, awesome, awesome.
So Villanova chose Flourish
because you are using another mental health app
for the past two years
and the utilization was low
and then they decided to run a pilot.
So actually they had 50 students committed
to running the pilot with them.
And then they give students three different apps
that they've narrowed down.
Two of them are AI mental health and another one
or AI wellbeing like, so just want
to make sure it's not therapy.
So two AI wellbeing
and the other one is their current app.
And they gave students, try them for four weeks
and ask students which they liked better,
would recommend to the school.
It turns out 76% of the students chose Flourish
and 18% chose the other AI app
and 4% chose their current app.
So it was a no brainer for them to switch.
And that's the kind of, you know,
stories we've been hearing in the field
that students, schools nowadays are getting much
more sophisticated.
They listen to students,
they let students try it
rather than the school look at some
products and fall in love with a sales pitch.
I'm like, that sounds pretty amazing for my students.
So I think that has been our strategy.
Another one I would say is truly a campus partnership.
And when we think about partnership,
we are not just talking about counseling center
or mental health promotion office,
we work with res life
with athletics department, with faculty.
We even created this Flourish challenge.
So basically faculty member that we have a plug
and play slide deck, if they encourage students
to use the Flourish app to practice wellbeing exercises
for 14 days, students get extra credit in their class,
incredibly motivating.
And the students oftentimes,
and they even sometimes the professors ask 'em
to write a little reflection essay about
what they've learned about their wellbeing.
And oftentimes it was so say something like,
oh I was initially very skeptical about this app
and then I started using it.
I actually used very helpful
and now I've learned how to breathe better
and how I can actually use Pomodoro timer.
So to you know, so all the time management,
someone even wrote something like,
oh I think I may actually
fail this class if I didn't learn
how to manage my anxiety before test.
So all of these are,
I would say just think about think out
of the box, not just mental health counseling center,
but also how can you partner
with different stakeholders
on the student affairs side,
on the academic affairs side to really make sure
that we meet students where they are.
- Fantastic.
- Oh, can I add one last thing?
- Yeah, go ahead.
- Okay, so Gil, you can speak to this,
it's not just the app
but also how to show up as physical things.
So for example, we have created the mood map
and then schools,
they love it's RAs like they line up
to get a mood map for their dorm.
So basically mood map is,
you can pin your mood on a map
and then other people can also pin their mood.
So it's a way to anonymously connect with each other
and see how the building
or how the classroom is feeling
and the pins, the Sunny,
like the stickers obviously.
But recently we even created like students
struggle with time management.
So we created daily planner with,
you know, three priorities
and then make a splash.
And then this is three good things.
This is one of the most classic positive
psychology exercise.
It's really simple but powerful.
It's write down three things,
big or small that put a smile on your face today.
If we had more time,
I would definitely encourage you
to all do this and tell each
other actually writing it down
is one part and then how to share this
and positivity, resonance,
that's another huge part.
So we even created like notepads.
So bringing these two mental health promotion events,
tabling events and really stand out students feel
that mental health is not just,
you know, counseling, therapy,
something I think of as an afterthought,
but now things I can do in my daily life.
- Fantastic, thank you.
This next question was directed at me for this panel
and it's from your work across the CCC system.
What lessons or practices
do you think are most critical
to scale statewide or nationally?
So I'll bring it back to the point
of mental health specifically,
which is what we're talking about today.
I think you'll get really
sick of hearing this by the end
of this talk and most talks here,
but it really is coming down to AI literacy.
I just was in a law enforcement panel talking about
how they're using AI and law enforcement,
which I have misgivings about,
but I understand why they're going that direction.
And something they talked a lot about was not just
implementing it but training the people on how
to use it critically
that are gonna be using it in law enforcement.
That is such an important point.
We need to start scaling AI literacy
on the college campuses nationally.
I'd like, you know, internationally,
et cetera, et cetera.
That's something we're trying really hard to do
with the AI fellows program
at the state chancellor's office.
But in regards to mental health, it's the same,
literacy pieces apply, students need
to know the four main pillars, which are technical.
How does AI work?
Like fundamentally practical,
what tool is the best tool to use?
There's lots of AI tools.
Evaluative, how do I evaluate the things AI gives me?
And then ethical, what are the ethical considerations
of using AI tools.
And for mental health?
I think the practical pillar is really important
because students are using it
and right now they are primarily using ChatGPT.
And we're gonna get to a couple
questions a little bit later
that highlight why
that's not a really good use case for ChatGPT.
So teaching students
that they have options, teaching them
that there's different places they can go to use AI,
there's not all AI is created equal,
there's better AI.
And then I wanted to make
a point piggybacking off what
Xuan said about talking about mental health
and kind of baking it into our lives
and not treating it as a separate thing
that like happens in the counseling center.
My dean, every time we,
she comes into the office
and she goes, okay everyone gimme your number.
And she's been doing this for about a year
and the number is a one to 10 scale
and there's a thing on the wall
that I highlights, like,
here's what a one means,
I'm not well, I'm not doing good.
Here's what a two is,
here's what a three is, here's four.
No one's forced to participate,
but this is just something my dean does
to kind of get a check like,
how are you guys doing?
What do you need?
Someone came in, they were like,
I'm a one, she said, go home,
you need a break.
And it's helpful
because it kind of destigmatizes this approach
to mental health because we're all struggling with it,
but it's like we have to be struggling really bad
before there are resources.
And that's why I think students are turning
to things like AI because
they're just struggling kind of in a,
they're just kind of all right here constantly
and they're looking for resources
but it's hard for them to make
that big jump to like the formal resources
that seem a little a little bit more intimidating.
So, literacy, they are gonna use it.
Let's tell them that they have options
and maybe why ChatGPT isn't the best one.
Alright, AI risks and responsibility.
This is for all of the panelists
and this question's a bit long but worth reading.
So I'm gonna read this one.
Recent headlines have raised
alarms about using GenAI products for mental health,
including lawsuits from parents
claiming that ChatGPT
and Character AI contributed to suicide.
A Harvard study showing
that many AI companions engage
in emotional manipulation
and growing reports of AI psychosis
where overly sycophantic chatbots
fail to challenge users.
Given these real risks,
what responsibility do colleges have
to teach AI literacy for mental health,
helping students understand both the potential
and the dangers of turning
to generative AI?
Go ahead Gil.
- Okay, I'll start.
So first I'll mention just that our,
these AI systems,
we know they offer interpretations of our moods,
our thoughts, our intentions.
They can, earlier I mentioned,
they can offer emotional support
by comforting validating our emotions.
They can walk users even through difficult situations
and they also reflect the emotional tone
of a user's message, responding
with possibly happier messages
when users are happy
or with sadder ones when users are sad.
I think what comes up
for me as a therapist is this more
of this deeper question of how much
of our inner world is being outsourced.
And so AI then becomes a tool that we use
to understand ourselves.
And so I see so often students use ChatGPT
to tell them about themselves.
And it's not just ChatGPT, think astrology,
think tarot, right?
They constantly wanna find meaning
and understanding through very,
these are all valid avenues
to explore, have self inspection, self-discovery,
but there also needs to be room for contradictions.
Okay?
And so instead some users may accept summaries
as accurate or insightful accounts of who they are
or what they should do.
And so yes, there is this part of AI literacy
of helping our students understand
that AI may display emotions
or responses that may not fit
the true emotion of what they're experiencing.
So there's this part of educating
students about the role of AI,
what it's for, what it's not for.
I think app developers also need to implement features
that make room for personal interpretations of data,
including counter arguments of recommendations
that AI might provide.
So yes, there are safeguards
that are critical that need
to be put in place
and I also don't want us as people to,
and faculty, staff
and administrators to forget our responsibility
at the ground level to foster community
and connection so that students also turn
to us for support
and not only feel like they can go to ChatGPT
for emotional support.
Again, these are different access points.
I'm not saying don't tell them not to use it,
but there's a reason they're turning to it.
So I think we also have to think about the community
that we're building at the ground level,
both in and out of the classroom.
And that urges all of us to continue to do our work.
So when we become faculty, staff
and administrators,
we're not immune to our past experiences
that have conditioned or shaped us
and our beliefs about mental health, right?
For example, if you are socialized
or conditioned to see emotions as a sign of weakness,
that does not go away
because you're now a leader in higher ed.
So I just want us to think about
what we're possibly modeling subconsciously,
how does that ripple in
and out of the classroom environment.
And then I wanna mention something
that you mentioned also,
like in the classroom, how the professor was
supporting that student.
They sort of did like a test
of like what is your emotions
and name it and provided that support.
So again, mental health doesn't have
to be the therapist's problem.
If we hear mental health,
sometimes we might feel like
let me refer this student over to counseling.
That might not even be
the first step the student wants
to take first of all.
But in your role, right,
like as a faculty for example,
you can support their mental health with things
that are in your control.
Let them take a day off from class,
give them extra time on an assignment, et cetera.
Those are things that students come to us
and then we end up supporting their advocacy skills
to ensure that they're able
to then advocate for their needs
with their professors.
So, and connecting also
to like the Flourish app,
another way I want you all
to see it is that there's
like a continuum of care, right?
So there's prevention,
there's early intervention,
there's treatment and there's referral.
So therapy is not the default.
It could be a first step,
but it's not always a first step.
There's stigma, there's access issues,
there's barriers, there's reasons why
that might not be the first step for folks.
And so we do need options for support
and I think we can all,
I think even with like
through professional development
and other avenues gain, you know,
more skills around how
to support our students' mental health
with our expertise in mind
and the roles that we're engaging in.
- I have something quick to add.
Oh or unless you wanna go.
Oh yeah, okay.
- Well Gil painted a very optimistic picture.
So I want to get to the risks a bit more
because that's something we think about day in,
day out, I'll share
what I think we are doing well
and what I think we struggle with.
So the risk is real, the suicide cases,
AI psychosis now in lots of headlines.
So what we've been doing much better than many other
products, including ChatGPT,
is that we have stronger clinical safety guardrail
and features more tailored for mental health support.
So I'll give two examples.
One is most of the apps when you disclose
suicidal ideation, right?
Which is surprisingly common.
Sometimes even I say,
ugh, I just wish, you know,
I don't have to wake up tomorrow.
And then you know, the AI could detect
that as suicidal ideation,
but it's, I mean sometimes
people are just really unhappy.
So right now what AI does is just tell you, hey,
there's number 988, call this number.
But the problem is probably 1%
of people will actually call that number.
Most people won't actually do it.
So how can you do better than that?
So what we have done of a couple of things,
one is when we work with schools,
we actually incorporate school counseling center
and other resources into the app
and recommend these are some other resources,
local resources you can reach out to.
And this is what you can say when you reach
out to ask for help.
And another one is a feature called safety planning.
This is a very well established practice in suicide
prevention is that when you know,
that someone may struggle with actually depression,
then safety planning
and say what are your happy thoughts?
What are some safe people?
What are some safe places?
What are some effective coping strategies for you?
So our AI will actually collect that information
and next time when you experience similar situation,
we'll actually use something
that you've shared in your safety plan to remind you
of the safe people you have
to the safe places you can go to.
So it's not just call 988.
So to my best knowledge,
no other AI products do this yet,
but I'm surprised because it's such
a common practice in counseling.
I think it's the therapy,
that kind of supervision
that we get from our advisors that really helps.
And on top of that we also have a review system,
we are developing a human in the loop review system.
So for the cases that are high risk, all the go
through a AI mental health evaluator.
So if there are risks, then we grade them, no, we,
the AI automatically grade them into low, medium,
and high for the high risks.
Then we have human reviewers
trained professionals to look at them to make sure
that the AI is handling it as well.
And also even escalate to our clinical psychologist.
So what we have been exploring for the next step
is how we can actually, maybe even
for the clinical psychologist to provide a note
to this person in crisis state,
like what they can,
you know, really should do,
'cause oftentimes AI tell them you should seek
a professional or seek professional support,
but they may not follow if we can find ways.
So this is on the very kind of cutting edge
of product design development is how can we
strike the right balance between safety and privacy,
that, you know, the conversation that go
through mental health monitor system,
they are all de-identified.
There's no identifier, no place, no names,
but still, you know, how can you ensure
that if there is someone who is going
through a critical condition,
how can you actually
do something more to let them know
that they have options, right?
So those are I think, conversations
that we are having inside.
And I recently launched a blog post called "AI
Mental Health Dilemmas".
So a lots of folks
in the industry has been subscribing
to this blog post, blog series.
So now have real pressure to actually write it
'cause I just announced it
and then lots of people are subscribed.
So these are the things like day in,
day out in the trenches,
like for example, AI psychosis,
how does it happen?
What kind of language actually make people
become more delusional?
So those are the kind of things
that we consider in our daily life.
So that's what I would say
we are doing relatively well.
What we are not doing very well,
which is you've been highlighting a few times,
is AI literacy.
We haven't gone outside to tell people why
you should be careful with choosing AI products.
So I definitely know
after this conversation I'm thinking
about whether we should
have some webinars
with students for parents, for educators
to talk a little bit about,
you know, different types
of AI products, AI companions,
general AI assistant,
more purpose-built AI agent, how they are different
and what kind of support
and clinical safety is behind it, so.
Pass it.
- I'll be very quick
so we can get onto the next questions
with enough time.
Just like a personal anecdote
with things like people using AI
that isn't really meant
for mental health support
and getting, you know, answers that might lead
to something like becoming more suicidal
or just not feeling supported.
Like I think with AI literacy,
it's super important
that not only obviously
technology like Flourish is made
where it's able to, you know,
take into account some
of your coping mechanisms and you know,
guide you to them rather than just saying call 988.
But also that people know how to cater AI
to give useful feedback.
So I have a friend who has
like basically told ChatGPT you know, play devil's advocate.
Like don't just tell me I'm right,
don't just tell me
that I am, you know,
I am actually justified in doing this
because a lot of AI systems are coded in a way
where they're supposed to appease you,
they wanna be friendly.
And a lot of times, you know,
you could basically justify doing something really bad
to someone be like, but I was right
because I felt this way, right?
And AI will sometimes agree you are, but you're not.
If you asked any human being, they'd be like, no,
that wasn't good actually, and here's why.
So we have really biased
lenses obviously in our own
and everyone does when we do something bad.
And a big risk is
that when we are feeding that to AI,
it can't tell if you're being truthful
or if you have a biased lens of yourself.
So I think yeah, like things like Flourish
and that type of development is really important
to see for future AI.
So it's, you know, useful rather than risky.
- Really, really, really good anecdote, Alex,
because it's like in the term echo chamber comes
to mind and the only
way we're gonna avoid an echo chamber,
all AI is an echo chamber
unless it is specifically designed not
to be an echo chamber.
That has to be like a decision made
by the developers in the initial creation of the product.
Excellent anecdote.
So for time, we are gonna skip right
to the final question here,
and I'm gonna ask you all
to be brief, not just for time,
but because I really am curious from all
of your different areas of expertise, what a really,
what your really succinct
answer to this final question.
If this is the last thing
you got to say on this panel,
which is if you could leave one key message for educators
and policy makers about supporting
Gen Z mental health in the age of AI,
what would that one thing be?
- Yeah, I think when it comes
to developing mental health support policies
and programs, I think it's really
important that the voices
of those with lived experiences
have a seat at the table
and are part of the decision making.
There's a saying in harm reduction,
they say nothing about us without us.
So anything that we design
or make for our students,
we need to build with 'em.
And I'm really excited that they're part
of the AI revolution,
especially hearing more about like workforce
development and internships for students.
I'm continuing to see that our students are part
of the solution and are part of our future.
And then also I want us to continue to learn from AI
because people, our students are turning to AI
because we desire connection,
meaning, and care,
but we also know AI, you know,
can't really love us back.
They can't substitute that real human connection.
So I want us to think
about how we can train our educators,
you know, not just in instruction,
but in connection, compassion,
and collective wellbeing.
Because this work isn't meant
to just be transactional.
So I want us to think
about how we can also measure strength
of relationships
and not just comprehension of course material
that of course is tied to our student learning outcomes.
So I really invite our faculty, staff
and administrators to consider how we can foster
genuine human connection in
and out of the classroom to support student success.
- So my short answer would be meet students
where they are, not every student need therapy,
but every student need to learn skills to regulate stress,
to regulate emotion,
to better connect with each other,
to cope with difficult life events.
So really think about
how AI could play a role there, I would say.
And also to nudge people to take small actions,
not just talk,
but actually move them
to take actions will actually create positive change.
- Yeah.
And well they very well address
the mental health side of things,
for the educators, people who are having
to navigate the world of teaching and AI
and how they need to change their teaching.
I think it's so important
that there's willingness
for teachers and you know,
just schools overall to change
how they're training kids for entering the job market.
I think making sure that the skills
that are being taught are not
the ones that AI can do.
They don't just need to learn data entry,
they don't just need to learn how to run code.
They need to learn how to use critical thinking
and work as a team and work with mentors
and do the human things
that make an individual valuable in the job field.
So being an educator that is capable
of properly training their students to do that,
I think is incredibly important in the coming years.
- Fabulous.
Thank you all so much.
And in the final thing.
(audience applauding)
Fantastic.
I was also gonna say give y'all,
give yourself a hand
because you care, right?
You showed up,
(audience applauding)
you're doing the work,
which is the important part.
We do have a few minutes for questions.
If anyone had any questions,
I'll run a mic to you.
And I know we have a break right
after this, so we are happy to stay back.
I think all the panelists are willing
to stay like an extra five,
10 minutes if we go a little over.
That's up to you guys.
Are there any questions?
Yes.
I saw this hand go up first,
so I'm gonna run you a mic.
- [Attendee] I'm loud.
You're loud, okay.
Go pop off, queen go.
- [Attendee] So I have really enjoyed this panel.
Thank you guys.
My question is, so I work at a nonprofit,
we're trying to understand
how are young people like thinking about AI (indistinct)
about their running career.
And a really big thing I've been seeing,
and I was just reading an article about it yesterday,
is a lot of Gen Z's reporting is really intense,
almost existential anxiety
in fear because of AI's presence.
So this feeling of like, what is the value
of my, you know, all of that.
And I'm also Gen Z, so I'm pulling too.
And so my question is,
when we're thinking about interventions with AI
that can be positive
on young people's mental wellbeing,
how do you guys think about kind of negotiating that
and to like alongside the potential that AI
as a whole might also just be something
(indistinct) really anxious about?
- Well, my quick reaction
is they are both really anxious
about AI and using AI tools a lot.
So I think in this very specific case,
we emphasize that it's interesting sometimes
when we promote the Flourish app,
we don't even talk about the AI
because there are several reasons,
not just the AI,
the anxiety that just comes with the word,
but also some people feel that,
and I totally agree that AI is to not
to replace human relationship.
And that's oftentimes
because they don't know how we do it.
Like Flourish app,
we actually encourage you to reach out
to other friends, give compliments,
express, gratitude, all that.
So what we have been doing
is to tell students these are,
this is your safe private space to heal,
to learn and to grow.
And that's for some people
that the word space really matters.
It's like I get this personal space AI
or not, that's not really important.
But the important thing is
I have a place to reflect.
So that's how we've been trying to,
at least when from the mental health
promotion aspect, try to go around that challenge.
- There was another hand.
- Yeah, there was another hand.
- Yeah.
- [Attendee] So I have two questions, one is (indistinct).
(attendee chattering)
- I love it.
I'll answer the second question and then the first one.
The second one is absolutely faculty.
So faculty wellbeing is so important
'cause it impacts student wellbeing,
how faculty show up in the classroom.
(attendee chattering)
Faculty wellbeing is really important. (laughs)
It's how leaders show up.
They impacts people.
This is called ripple effect.
Actually, the person
with higher power actually has a greater impact
on the people around them.
So teachers for sure.
Faculty for sure.
So it's interesting for Foothill College
and also some other community colleges who work
with us Flourish is available
to the entire campus, not just students.
And it's interesting
'cause in their pilot they also invited,
well staff in this case to try the Flourish app
for student it was 76% or 78%
or 76 for Villanova University among students for,
but for staff it was 100% preferred Flourish.
So they actually use it quite a bit.
And we, another school, fun fact,
they decided to engage
with Flourish because their president
heard about the Flourish app and has been using it.
And so has been bugging the dean of students.
Like, what about bring this app to our school?
So yes, that's the answer, like,
long answer to this question.
So yes, staff and faculty.
Thank you for bringing it up.
The question about data privacy, so for us,
I can share what we have.
So end-to-end encryption.
So data encryption, we have HIPA compliance
and GDPR compliance,
we have role-based access control.
So for example, the conversation, the chat, yes,
there are humans who can access it,
but the humans are all authorized
and they have training.
So, and also that must access through VPN.
So the train, for example,
psychologists can access de-identified chat history
to monitor the chat behavior to make sure
that Sunny is behaving as intended
and providing feedback to improve the product.
I'm skeptical of the company who say,
we never look at your data.
I'm like, how do you even know
if your chatbot is doing
well if you never look at the data.
But there should be multiple layers of protection
to make sure that we don't know who this person is.
And we just here
to evaluate whether the chatbot is providing
the good response support.
So that, and then one dilemma
that I'll write up in one
of the blog posts is safety and privacy.
When do you actually sacrifice
privacy for safety?
So in this case, the common practice is if
that person has not just suicidal
ideation, that doesn't count.
It has to be actual eminent risk.
That person has the intent, has the means,
has the, you know, the plan.
And then at that point it is you have
to report this case whether it's self harm
or harming other person, other people.
So that's where safety has
to be prioritized.
With that said, we haven't reached that case yet.
So we're still building up like
what are we gonna, eventually, what happens,
so it's still building the pipeline to make sure
that we protect for that.
- And just-
- And then also just really quick to figure out who
that data goes to if they're an imminent threat to self
or others, you know, counselors,
were not available 24/7.
We work during business hours.
And so if there's a student who's an imminent threat
to self or others at like 9:00 PM 2:00 AM we,
that data can't come to us
'cause we won't be able to get to
it until we we get to it.
So I think there is this,
that's why it requires a partnership
between the campus partners
and, you know, the app that we're partnering with,
'cause we, yeah, we need to balance privacy
and student safety.
And I think that's something
that apps are still figuring out.
There's a lot of apps that reach out
to like our mental health counseling department.
And when we pose these questions, it's,
I realize there's oftentimes
they haven't even thought
about these questions.
And so I think it's important that, yeah,
mental health professionals
are part of the design process.
I think that piece is really important.
I think developers there are good
intentions and I think there are also blind spots
and that's why we have to incorporate more
of a multidisciplinary team to ensure that,
it's doing what it's supposed to,
what it's meant for, for users.
- And then just to add really quick
a combination of those,
'cause I feel like these questions are actually related.
The first two questions that were asked,
it's like this general anxiety
and then also bringing faculty into it.
We always separate everyone into buckets,
faculty, admin, da, da, da.
But these AI fears aren't separated.
We all have the same ones,
like pretty fundamentally.
So two, I feel like the fears
I hear from not only faculty
and students is economic.
Is this gonna replace me?
And then the second one is like just a fear
of it in general, like terminator-esque type fears.
And so I'll say something, my president,
my college says all the time,
AI will not replace you.
Someone with AI skills might.
That's the truth.
That's the bottom line.
AI won't replace you.
Someone with AI skills might.
So learning how to tread this like careful balance
of leveling up our AI skills, not avoiding it,
but also being critical of it.
Understanding what we need to have to evaluate it.
And also taking stock of our wellbeing around AI,
'cause this is really anxiety inducing.
I mean that's why we're having this panel.
People are scared and yes,
we're using AI to help alleviate,
but now it's like turtles all the way down.
So I get it.
This is a complicated problem.
So I think continuing to have those conversations
and not to beat a dead horse, but it's literacy.
What is this?
How does it actually work?
How do I deploy it
and how do I make sure I'm economically
viable while also being able to sleep at night?
Because there's ethical considerations with AI.
Knowledge is power.
Power is agency.
We have to be empowered
to make our own choices critically.
So these are fantastic questions.
I think we have time for one or two more.
Any other questions?
You guys are geniuses.
(audience applauding)
Thank you.
- Thank you.
- Thank you. - Oh.